Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 7 -- Letters to Franklin 1783 January-November Mss.B.F85inventory07
American Philosophical Society
- Letters to Benjamin Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 March 23; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Acknowledging Franklin's kind espousal of his cause with M. [Joly] de Fleury; finds the Minister will not grant the desired exception.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 March 23; A.L.S. 3p.; Croust, ----- Cordier de
    Induced by family troubles to seek solace in the land of liberty; asks for a passage for himself and four or five of his laborers.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 March 23; A.L.S. 3p.; Ludewig, Joachim Heinrich. Bützow
    Desires a position as professor of the German and Dutch languages at the University of Philadelphia, or as teacher of the historical and political sciences.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 March 24; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; La Rochefoucauld, Louis Alexandre, duc de
    Sending him the rough draft of a letter agreed upon yesterday; advises Franklin to hand it himself to the Comte de Vergennes the next day, or to speak to him about it. Adds his recommendation for the place of the United States Consul at Fécamp.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 March 24; A.L.S. 2p.; Poma, -----. Lorraine
    Desires to settle in America and practise medicine there.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 March 24; A.L.S. 1p.; Biedermann, Ehrenhold Fredric. Paris
    Reminding him of his promise to send him letters of recommendation to business houses in Philadelphia and Boston.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 March 24; A.L.S. 1p.; Mazue, -----. Marseilles
    His merchandise in America paid for in paper money, which is worthless; desires to know if Congress will give him the equivalent in land of the amount he lost.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 March 24; A.L.S. 4p.; Herman Heyman's Sons. Bremen
    Their vessel, the "Batavia," will leave for Charleston in about three weeks to bring back a cargo of rice; offering to carry anything over Franklin may wish to send.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 March 25; A.L.S. 1p.; MacMahon, John. At the Military school in Paris
    Introducing Mme. d'Herbigny, the daughter of Sir Walter Rutledge, an Irish gentleman; her desire to obtain a recommendation to the Comte de Vergennes.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 March 25; A.L.S. 1p.; Caffiéri, Jean Jacques
    Hears that the Americans intend raising a statue to the glory of the King; would be flattered to receive a commission for this monument.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 March 26; A.L.S. 2p.; Vaughan, Samuel Jr. Paris
    An account of certain changes in the administration. Meeting of a committee of American merchants and the address they drew up for the King.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 March 26; A.L.S. 2p.; Lotbinière, Michel-Alain Chartier de. Paris
    Concerning his two seignories at the head of Lake Champlain; memoir which the Comte de Vergennes will hand Franklin on this subject; begs that the papers may be returned to him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 March 26; A.L.S. 2p.; Cotte, Jules-François de. Paris
    Concerning the medals ordered by Franklin to be struck; account of a new metal imitating silver, which has been tried and found wanting.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 March 26; L.S. 2p.; Devoulx frères. Marseilles
    Sums owing to the firm by the United States; desires Franklin's advice as to the steps they must take to receive payment.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 March 26; A.L.S. 2p.; Herbigny, Marie-Julie Rutledge d’. Paris
    Account of the Rutledges and how they were ruined in the Stuart cause; a paralytic brother and a mother dependent on her; her husband a French officer and they have one child; desires the Comte de Vergennes to intercede with the King to procure her a pension; a Mr. Rutledge, a relation of hers, a member of the Congress.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 March 27; A.L.S. 2p.; Hopkinson, Francis. Philadelphia
    Manner in which the news of peace was received in America. Report of Franklin's intended return to America. His piece respecting trees. An account of a new game of cards he devised for the improvement of his children's spelling. A long letter he wrote to Franklin concerning a plot of Hopkinson's supposed friends to ruin him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 March 28; A.L.S. 18p.; Ferry, Gaspard-Bonaventure-Timothée. Marseilles
    His admiration for Franklin's discoveries and experiments; however believes that they do not rest on sufficient physical grounds; a long explanation of his own beliefs and observations, with remarks on Franklin's theory.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 March 28; A.L.S. 2p.; Ginette frères and Luc Laugier. Marseilles
    Concerning the capture of their brigantine, the "Maria Theresa," by an English corsair, and its recapture by a frigate belonging to the United States, by whom it was carried to Boston; enclosing a copy [3p.] of the official records entered at St. Pierre by the officers of the "Maria Theresa"; also a request for the restitution of the brigantine, by Pléville Le Pelley [1p.].
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 March 29; A.L.S. (by Proxy). 2p.; Steuben, Wilhelm Augustine von. Cüstrin
    Request to forward a letter to his son. Has not heard from General von Steuben. Doubts whether his letters have reached him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 March 29; A.L.S. 1p.; Strange, Robert. Paris
    Congratulations on the success of his glorious and indefatigable labors. A letter from Mrs. Strange in London mentions a visit from Franklin's son. Intends setting out for London on Thursday. Commits the enclosed letters to Franklin's care.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 March 29; A.L.S. 1p.; Büyck, Pierre. Gand
    Concerning a letter of exchange on which he wishes to realize the money.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 March 29; A.L.S. 3p.; Villiers, Louis-Pierre Dufourny de
    Introducing M. de Quernay, 1 Colonel in the Engineer Corps, who commanded at the siege of Yorktown.
    1 de la Combe de Querenet. (See Balch, The French in America during the War of Independence. II, 209, Philadelphia, 1895.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 March 29; L. 2p.; ------, ------
    Requests him to forward the enclosed letter to his son; asks him to acknowledge the receipt of his letters.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 March 30; A.L.S. 1p.; Froger de La Rigaudière, chevalier Louis Honoré. Paris
    About according a free port to the Seudre river and the Isle of Oléron.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 March 30; A.L.S. 1p.; Bartoli, Joseph. Paris
    His Italian verses, first printed in London, which predicted the success of the Americans in the late war: sends Franklin a copy.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 March 31; A.L.S. 1p.; Hoffmeister, H. Adolphe. Heidelberg
    Profits by Franklin's kindness to his brother-in-law and to himself to send him the enclosed.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 March 31; A.L.S. 4p.; Horn, ------. St. Petersburg
    Seeking the position of American Consul or Minister.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 March 31; A.L.S. 3p.; Lomagne-Tarride, vicomte de. Orthez
    Begs Franklin to grant him, at once, land in America sufficient for himself and several of his vassals; desires the colony to bear Franklin's name; thinks his demand Justified by his military services in America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 March 31; A.L.S. 4p.; H------, J------. Dublin
    Having observed in the public print the intention of the United States Commissioners in Paris to appoint agents in several of the ports of Great Britain, to correspond and regulate such matters as may be necessary between the two countries, the writer takes the liberty of offering his services to act as Agent for the port of Dublin or for Waterford or for both. States his claims and qualifications.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 1; A.L.S. 1p.; Beaujeu, comte ----- de.
    Sent Franklin a medal in silver gilt to be forwarded to Gen. Washington; joined to this a military chanson in honor of Franklin and Washington; begs for an acknowledgment.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 1; A.L.S. 3p.; Nogaret, François-Félix
    Acknowledging Franklin's recommendation of him to the Marquis of Serreul, for the position of Librarian.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 1; A.L.S. 3p.; The Burgomasters and Senators of the Republic of Hamburg
    Begging him to aid their merchants in forming commercial relations in America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 2; L.S. 2p.; Houdetot, Comtesse d'
    M. de Crevecoeur in great embrrassment from not having received Franklin's expected reply; importance of having it before his interview with M. de Castries.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 3; A.L.S. 1p.; Vaughan, Samuel Jr. Paris
    Desiring to borrow a sum of money for which he encloses a bill on his brother William.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 3; A.L.S. 4p.; F-----, J------. Wicklow
    His offer to further the interest of the United States and Ireland; this he will be able to do from his general knowledge of trade and of the commerce of both countries; articles whose export to America would prove profitable.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 3; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Sr
    Account of his arrival in London and the great civility shown him by Messrs. Vaughan, Hodgson and Laurence. Some facts about the new Ministry. Told it will take some time to remove all the King's troops from America. Death of Mrs. Stevenson.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 3; A.L.S. 7p.; Von Lilienstern, August Friedemann Rühle. Dillenburg
    Concerning German colonists to be sent to the United States. Has asked previously and fears colonists will apply to an English Agent or to Count Romanzow, Russian Ambassador at Frankfort. Wishes to be appointed United States Minister to various German districts. Plan of colonization.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 4; A.L.S. 3p.; Dubeaucage, ------. Marseilles
    His plan to establish a business house in America; begs for Franklin's advice and protection.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 4; A.L.S. 1p.; Desbrossée, ------. Le Mans
    Desires to go to America under Franklin's protection and procure a position as engineer or architect.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 5; A.L.S. 1p.; Kirwan, Andrew. Passy
    His distressed situation; hopes Franklin will assist him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 5; L.S. 1p.; Vergennes, Charles Gravier, comte de. Versailles
    Consenting to the publication in Paris of a translation of the Constitution of the United States, on condition that the sheets be forwarded to a censor for examination as fast as they shall be printed.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, IX, 508).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 6; A.L.S. 1p.; Coquillot, ------, abbé. Paris
    Offering his verses on peace.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 7; A.L.S. 1p.; Belletti, Dominique-François. Trieste
    Discusses his plan of forming a commercial alliance between Austria and America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 7; A.L.S. 2p.; Malarme, Charlotte de Bournon, comtesse de. Paris
    Her enthusiasm for America; send a copy of her second work; whatever remuneration he chooses to make for it will be gratefully received.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 7; L.S. 2p.; The Municipality of Port Louis
    Sending a memoir on their port; well adapted for a depot for the trade of the United States.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 7; A.L.S. 2p.; Turner, Catharine. Leigh Lancaster, Eng
    She married his nephew, John Mecom, and was a long time in his house in Philadelphia with Mrs. Franklin and Mrs. Bache; after Mr. Mecom's death, married Mr. Turner who died from wounds received in the war. Anxious to return to her native land and if possible procure a pension as the widow of an American officer.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 8; A.L.S. 2p.; Ingenhousz, Jan
    Desires to know if Franklin received his letters, one with a new east of his profile framed, another requesting to dedicate his book to him. No word received from [Samuel] Wharton or [Francis] Coffyn. Asks his advice about the safety of some money placed in the Public Loan Office at Boston. Question of Franklin's coming to Vienna. Readiness of the Emperor to acknowledge the independence of America. Talk of a commercial treaty with America; chief exports. Vexed at the delay in printing his book.
    Printed, in part, in Works (Sparks, IX, 501, Note).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 8; L.S. 1p.; Bowens, François-Jacques-Arnould. Ostend
    Has given the necessary directions to prevent Franklin's newspapers from being sent to him in future. Happy to have been of use to Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 8; A.L.S. 2p.; Bourdillon, -----. Montferrand
    Desires to buy a large tract of land near Williamsburg, which he and his family will ccupy.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 8; L. in 3d P.; Froger de Larigaudiére, -----, chevalier. Passy
    Relative to a request to the Comte de Vergennes for a free port near the Seudre river.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 9; A.L.S. 2p.; Floirac, abbé ----- de. Archbishop's Palace, Paris
    Desire of Mme. la Comtesse d'Anterroches to send her letters to her son in America in Franklin's care.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 9; A.L.S. 1p.; Mackinnen, William Jr. Paris
    Concerning two books Mr.Vaughan gave him for Mr.Adams.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 9; A.L.S. 2p.; Jones, Herbert. Llynon, Anglesea
    Desire of a number of Welshmen to emigrate to America; if Franklin approves, he and others will take to America a colony of at least one thousand people, mostly artificers.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 10; A.L.S. 3p.; Godfrey Grosser's Widow and Co. Leipzig
    Asks for the names of the best merchants in Philadelphia, and other ports, and for a list of the commodities which America most needs.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 10; A.L.S. 2p.; Utzschneider, Joseph. Munich
    Concerning a Bavarian company who are anxious to trade with America. Begs franklin for information relative to the articles most likely to sell in America and Europe; their intention of sending an agent to Philadelphia.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 10; A.L.S. 2p.; Galart, -----. Paris
    Will send Franklin a memoir setting forth the advantages which the port of Bayonne can offer to the United States if it were thrown open free to their commerce.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 11; A.L.S. 3p.; Coffyn, Francis. Dunkirk
    List of American prisoners whom he assisted with a little money during their stay in Dunkirk; has drawn on Franklin for the amount. Number of vessels despatched to North America since the conclusion of peace; his endeavor to promote the interest of the house of Bache and Shee of Philadelphia. Advantages the Port of Dunkirk offers to the American trade. Asking for a passport for Capt. Coreil's brig which sails for America under American colors.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 11; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Ségur, Philippe-Henri, marquis de
    Acknowledging the medal sent him by Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 11; A.L.S. 2p.; Belletti, Dominique-François. Trieste
    Intends sending a vessel to America for trade; no commercial treaty between Austria and America; desires to know if he is at liberty to sell his cargo there and purchase another for the return trip.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 11; A.L.S. 1p.; Bartoli, Joseph. Paris
    Acknowledging with enthusiasm Franklin's present of the medal; has attempted to put into verse a description of this ever glorious monument.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 11; A.L.S. 1p.; Grivel, Guillaume. Paris
    M. Canolle begs that the letter Franklin promised him may be sent by the post.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1783.] April 11; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Fleury, Joly de
    Thanking Franklin for sending him the medal.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 11; A.L.S 4p.; Halbach and fils, Jean and Gaspar
    Begging Franklin to grant them a letter of recommendation to Congress, so that they may receive orders to supply the American army and fleet with arms of all kinds; the reputaion of their house; possibility of establishing a house in Philadelphia; enclosing list of the arms manufactured by them.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 12; L in 3d P. 1p.; Amelot de Chaillou, Antoine-Jean. Versailles
    Acknowledging with expressions of gratitude the medal sent him by Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 12; A.L.S. 2p.; Hilliard d’Auberteuil, Michel-René. Paris
    Begs for the design of the medals struck by order of Congress, and of the mausoleums erected through Franklin's influence; a copy of these designs asked for by the book-seller to the King of Prussia, who is getting out an almanac in commemoration of the glorious revolution.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 12; A.L.S. 2p.; Perrot de Chezolles, -----. Paris
    Enclosing a memoir from the inhabitants of La Ciotat, asking that their port may enjoy the same liberties and franchises as Bayonne in favor of the United States.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 12; A.L. in 3d P. 2p.; La Rochefoucauld, Louis Alexandre, duc de
    Thanks Franklin for his fine medal. Asks him to send him the "Treaty with Sweden" and the "Preface." as the printer is waiting for them.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 13; A.L.S. 2p.; Grasse, François-Joseph-Paul, comte de. Paris
    Extremely flattered at receiving the medal sent him by Franklin. Will always remember how fortunate he was in having formed and carried out the project of taking Yorktown.
    (In French.) 1
    1 An incorrect translation of this letter is printed in Hale's Franklin in France, II, 263.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 13; A.L.S. 1p.; Saint-Auban, Jacques-Antoine Baratier, marquis de
    Acknowledging with many thanks the medal sent him by Franklin. He and Madame de St. Auban expect Franklin to dine with them soon after Easter.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 13; A.L.S. 1p.; Deux-Ponts, Marianne Camasse, duchesse La douairière de
    Asking permission to bring a great friend of theirs, M. Delisle, to dine with Franklin. Thanking him for the medal.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1783.] April 13; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Walterstorff, ----- de
    Is prevented from accepting Dr. Franklin's invitation to dinner.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 13; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Castries, M de
    The ship "La Pintade" about to sail for America; begs Franklin to send any packets he may have for that country.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 13; A.L.S. 1p.; Palteau de Veimerange, Gabriel-Claude
    Acknowledging, with thanks, the medal sent him by Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 14; A.L.S. 1p.; Beaumont, Jean-Baptiste-Jacques Elie de
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 14; A.L.S. 3p.; Stockar zur Sonnenbourg, ----
    Criticism of the Abbé Raynal's works and style; prefers to translate the English pamphlets which he owes to Franklin. Recommending a friend who desires to go to America; would be glad to leave for America himself. Their pretended Helvetian freedom is gradually disappearing.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 14; A.L.S. 1p.; Belletti, Dominique-François. Trieste
    Desiring Franklin to forward the enclosed letter to Philadelphia.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 14; A.L.S. 2p.; Grobert, L.J. de [Jacques-François-Louis?]. Marseilles
    Unable to carry out his project of writing the History of the American Revolution in Italian. Desires to found an asylum in America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1780] April 15; L.S. 1p.; Baillivy, Chevalier de
    He and his brother desire to obtain employment in America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 15; L. in 3d P. 2p.; The Ambassador of the Emperor of Austria
    Requesting letters of introduction for Professor Märter who is about to set out for America on a tour of the world, having been appointed by the Emperor to secure a collection of animals and plants for His Majesty's zoological and botanical gardens.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 15; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Vaughan, Samuel Jr.
    Sending the first number of [Simon Nicolas Henri] Linguet's memoir on the Bastille; will send the second and third as soon as they come to hand; begs for their return as soon as Franklin has read them, as they are in great request.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 15; A.L.S. 1p.; Saint-Mars, Philippe de. Nantes
    Sending Franklin an ode which he has composed on the peace.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 16; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Castries, M de
    Acknowledging the packet sent him by Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 16; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Sr
    Sending Franklin an abridged edition of the Common Prayer Book. Prefers London to any place he ever saw. Expectation among Franklin's friends of seeing him in England.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 16; A.L.S. 2p.; Greenleaf, Thomas. Paris
    Sending a memoir in favor of their compatriot, M. Fanning, detained in the prison at Dunkirk; the cause of this detention is an accusation of theft against some of his crew; protests against such treatment; begs Franklin's intercession with the Minister of the King.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 17; A.L.S. 2p.; Pioger, ----- de
    Sending a certificate in favor of M. Le Febvre de Villeu.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1783?] April 17; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Jay, Sir James. Paris
    Begs for a speedy answer to his letter as he leaves Paris in a day or two.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 18; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Saint-Auban, Jacques-Antoine Baratier, marquis de and Geneviève Gruyn. Paris
    Their expectation of entertaining Franklin at dinner on the following Wednesday.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 17; A.L.S. 2p.; de Pioger, -----. Abbeville
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1783?] April 17; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Jay, Sir James. Paris
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 18; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Saint-Auban, Jacques-Antoine Baratier, marquis de and Geneviève Gruyn. Paris
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 18; L in 3d P. 1p.; Choisy, Messrs. de and de Béville
    Called to thank Franklin for the Medal which he sent them.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 18; A.L.S. 1p.; Beaujeu, comte ----- de. Champlitte
    Thanking him for the medal.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 18; A.L.S. 1p.; Kéralio, Agathon Guynement, chevalier de
    Expressing his appreciation of the medal.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 18; A.L.S. 6p.; Wintmülle, J.M. Hambourge
    The decision of Congress to establish a regular army in America; their offer of a prize for the best kind of powder for cannon, rifles, etc. Recommends a friend who has had a wide military experience and has made many valuable discoveries for the improvement and perfecting of muskets; report that General Washington intends visiting Paris in the spring. Has in his possession a secret method of Gilding with imitation gold which in appearance and durability is superior to the real thing. Offers to procure him some books by Scandinavian Philosophers.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 19; N. in 3d P. 1p.; Watson, Ellkanah. London
    Sending Dr. Franklin a few papers.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 19; L.S. 1p.; Duchemin, Daniel. Paris
    Begs Franklin's influence with M. de Ségur that he may be given the Hotel d' lnvalide.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 20; L. in 3d. P. 1p.; Saint-Auban, Jacques-Antoine Baratier, marquis de and Geneviève Gruyn. Paris
    Extremely sorry not to have the pleasure of Franklin's company at dinner on the day appointed; delighted to receive him on the 25th.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 20; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Pio, Luigi de
    Expressing his gratitude for the medal.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 April 21; A.L.S. 2p.; Deux-Ponts, Marianne Camasse, duchesse La douairière de